Guide to the Jefferson Franklin Ray, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jefferson Franklin Ray, Jr. papers
1837-1990
1920-1955
MS 1607
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
The Jefferson Franklin Ray, Jr. Papers consist of correspondence, professional papers, personal papers and photographs that document Ray's private life, family and career. The bulk of the collection chronicles Ray's education at Yale University and professional career as a diplomat and administrator in East Asia from 1920 to 1953. There is also documentation on other family members, including Ray's father, Jefferson Franklin Ray, Sr., who served as a missionary in Japan.
Ray, J. Franklin (Jefferson Franklin), 1905-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anne C. Ray, Gerda W. Ray, Jefferson F. Ray, III, Lester A. Ray, and Louis H. Ray, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Jefferson Franklin Ray, Jr. was born in 1905 to Daisy Winston Pettus and Jefferson Franklin Ray, Sr., Baptist missionaries in Kobe, Japan. Ray was raised in Japan, but returned to the United States and attended Vanderbilt University from 1922 to 1923, before transferring to Yale University. He completed his B.A. at Yale in 1926 (Phi Beta Kappa) and studied philosophy and psychology at the Yale University School of Graduate Studies from 1926 to 1929. He worked as an investment counselor in New Haven and New York before becoming the assistant director of the Surplus Division of the Federal Commodities Association in 1934. Ray joined the staff of the New York City Employment and Resources for Emergency Relief Bureau in 1935 and was employed there for the next two years. After four more years working as an investment counselor and with the onset of World War II, Ray served as a special assistant to the American ambassador to China from 1942 to 1945, and as special staff officer to commanding generals in the United States Army in the Chinese, Burmese and Indian theaters from 1941 to 1945. In 1945, Ray became assistant lend-lease administrator and chief of the China division of the Foreign Economic Administration.
From 1945 to 1947, Ray served as director of the Far Eastern office of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) and as acting director of the China office in 1946. He supervised allocations of relief supplies and assistance to China, reorganized and directed the program, and supervised personnel during a period of Chinese social upheaval and tense United Nations policy debate. UNRRA supplies were regularly denied to Communist-controlled areas and diverted to Nationalist-governed regions. Ray and hundreds of other UNRRA employees protested this strategy and sought to deliver relief supplies and support to all Chinese, despite international objections and frequent Chinese Nationalist blockades. Ray published his authorized history, The UNRRA in China, in 1947, detailing UNRRA's ambitions and evaluating its performance. In 1948, the Communist Chinese government awarded Ray the Special Cravat of the Brilliant Star for his humanitarian service as an UNRRA director.
Over the next few years, Ray worked in various advisory and administrative capacities in Korea and other East Asian countries. He was employed by the Department of State, the Committee for the Marshall Plan, the United Nations, the U.S. Educational and Informational Survey Mission to Korea, the United States Far Eastern Commission and the Economic Cooperation Administration's Mission to Korea. Because of his associations with the Institute for Pacific Relations and Alger Hiss, his popularity with Chinese Communists and support for distributing UNRRA supplies to Communist-controlled regions of China, Ray was brought before the Economic Cooperation Administration's Review Board in 1949. Ray was found to be a loyal United States employee, but his reputation was severely damaged. From 1951 to 1953, Ray served as the chief of the Geneva Liaison Office of the United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency. After failing to secure government work commensurate with his diplomatic skills and experience, Ray found work in the United States as an investment counselor at Bache & Company, and then as a vice-president of Bayrock, an investment firm, before retiring in 1971
Ray married three times. Ray and Mary Sharretts Haamman were wed in 1934 and divorced in 1945. In 1946, Ray married Hilda Austern, a fellow UNRRA employee, who died in 1971. Later that year, Ray married Martha Henrietta Weinert, who died in 1976. J. Franklin Ray, Jr. died on February 22, 1991, in Santa Fe, New Mexico, where he had just begun a new career teaching Japanese to elementary school students. He was survived by his children: Jefferson F. Ray, III, Louis H. Ray, Lester A. Ray, Gerda W. Ray, and Anne C. Ray
Scope and Contents
The Jefferson Franklin Ray, Jr. Papers consist of correspondence, professional papers, personal papers and photographs that document Ray's private life, family and career. The bulk of the collection chronicles Ray's education at Yale University and professional career as a diplomat and administrator in East Asia from 1920 to 1953. There is also documentation on other family members, including Ray's father, Jefferson Franklin Ray, Sr., who served as a missionary in Japan.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, 1905-1990, n.d. II. Professional Papers, 1933-1973, n.d. III. Personal and Family Papers, 1837-1981, n.d. IV. Photographs, 1879-1961, n.d.
United States -- Foreign relations -- China; China -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- Korea; Korea -- Foreign relations -- United States; Missionaries -- Japan; Ray, J. Franklin (Jefferson Franklin), 1905-; Holland, W. L. (William Lancelot), 1907-; Gould, Randall Chase, 1898-1979; Pettus, William B. (William Bacon), 1880-1959; Ray, Jefferson Franklin; United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration; United States. Economic Cooperation Administration; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1905-1990, undated; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence between Ray and his family, friends, and professional associates, arranged alphabetically. The most substantive correspondence relates to Ray's service with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration in China and the Economic Cooperation Administration, from 1945 to 1949. Ray's exchanges with fellow administrators and diplomats document UNRRA's efforts to distribute supplies and aid to war-damaged areas of China, where starvation and poverty were rampant and needed supplies were often blocked by Chiang Kai-Shek's American-backed Nationalist government. Correspondence with Colonel Fred D. Harris and UNRRA Director Generals Fiorello LaGuardia, Herbert Lehman and Lowell Rooks documents UNRRA activities in China. Although most of the correspondence between Ray and his second wife, Hilda Austern Ray, is personal, she also worked with the UNRRA in China, so the two frequently discussed the organization's activities.
  Ray regularly reviewed Chinese culture and politics with his uncle, William B. Pettus, who headed the California College in China and the Peking Museum. Ray's extensive correspondence with friend Randall Gould, editor of the Shanghai Evening Post, includes thorough, candid discussions of China and UNRRA, and a January 1948 exchange concerns Ray's friendship with Alger Hiss. Correspondence with Mary H. Ray, his first wife, also refers to this friendship. Ray rarely discussed professional matters with family members. Ray's correspondence with his brother Hermon S. Ray primarily concerns his brother's long career as a minister in Hawaii.
  - A, 1941-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1939-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bruce, Elizabeth, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1941-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Currie, Lauchlin, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D-F, 1939-1952, 1976-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Edgerton, Glen [major-general, director, UNRRA China office], 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. [approval of Ray's appointment to UNRRA China office], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - G, 1942-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gould, Randall [editor, Shanghai Evening Post], 1947-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - H, 1937-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Harris, Fred D. [acting chief, UNRRA Far Eastern affairs], 1946-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hazell, Charles and Emily Ray, 1926-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Holland, William. [secretary general, Institute of Pacific Relations], 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hoose, Saidee, 1937-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - I-K, 1942-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Kingsley, Donald [agent general, United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency], 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - L, 1939-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - LaGuardia, Fiorello H. [director general, UNRRA], 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lehman, Herbert [director general, UNRRA], 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - M, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mayer, Laura, 1946-1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - N, 1940-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - O-P, 1941-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Pettus, William B, 1941-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - R, 1939-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ray, Celeste Balfour, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Ray, Daisy Pettus, 1905-1943, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ray, Jefferson Franklin, Sr. [includes letters to/from family members], 1907-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
  - Ray, Hermon S., 1922-1990 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
  - Ray, Hilda Austern, 1946-1952, undated (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Ray, Mary Elisabeth, 1923-1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Ray, Mary H., 1942-1950 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Rooks, Lowell [director general, UNRRA], 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Rusk, Dean [brief letters regarding United Nations Secretariat and employment], 1947, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - S, 1941-1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
  - Shor, Franc [executive officer, UNRRA], 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Stettinus, E. R. [administrator, Lend-Lease Administration; under-secretary of state], 1941-1946 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - T, 1941-1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - U-Z, 1943-1973 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - First name only, 1944-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Letter fragments, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
- Professional Papers, 1933-1973, undated; Series II
  This series is comprised of professional papers, arranged alphabetically by subject, which primarily document J. Franklin Ray, Jr.'s service in China and Korea from 1942 to 1951. Ray selected UNRRA correspondence of historical value for Jean Herriot's paper, "The UNRRA China Program." These important memos and letters circulated between Ray and other central figures of UNRRA in China. The "Critique" folder contains a draft of an undelivered, angry letter Ray drafted to UNRRA Director General Fiorello LaGuardia, that indicates the extremity of Ray's frustration with the organization, the American government, and the Chinese Nationalists. The remainder of the UNRRA documents includes correspondence, publications, research, notes, press clippings, memos, correspondence, and weekly reports.
  "Hearing, Economic Cooperation Administration Review Board" contains legal documents and correspondence from Ray's 1949 hearing, at which Ray successfully defended himself against charges of disloyalty and Communist sympathy. "Employment" contains resumes, recommendations, reports and samples of work. The latter were compiled by Ray to evidence his professional experience prior to 1953 and span the breadth of his career.
  - Emergency Relief Bureau, New York Division of Work Referral, 1934-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Employment
    - Recommendations, 1942-1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Resumes and reports, 1948-1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Samples of work, 1935-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Federal Surplus Relief Corporation, 1933-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Foreign Affairs Committee, United States House of Representatives. [Ray's staff consultant appointment and related press releases], 1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Korea
    - Economic Cooperation Administration
      - "Draft Summary Paper: Counterpart Program for Korean Fiscal Year 1950-1951" (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Finances, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - General, 1941-1945, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Hearing, Economic Cooperation Administration Review Board
        - Affidavits and letters, 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
        - Exhibits, 1943-1949 (Box 7, Folder 13)
        - Selected materials, 1948-1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - "Revision of the ECA Program in Korea" [memo by Ray], 1950 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - General, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Memos, 1950-1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Notes and journals, 1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - "Unfinished Business in Korea" [article by Ray], 1947-1948, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Lend-Lease Administration and Foreign Economic Administration, 1942-1945 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - UNRRA in China
    - Chinese Special Cravat of the Brilliant Star, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1946-1948 (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - Herriot, Jean ["The UNRRA China Program" by Herriot, and Ray's selected UNRRA correspondence], 1946-1966 (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
    - Critique [unsent letter, addressed to UNRRA Director General Fiorello LaGuardia], undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - General, 1946-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - "Hunger Fighters" [UNRRA-China publication], 1952, 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 27-28)
    - Mao speech, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Press clippings, 1946, undated (Box 8, Folder 30-32)
    - Reports [weekly progress], 1946 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - "The Story of UNRRA" [UNRRA publication], 1948 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - "UNRRA in China" [by Ray]
      - Paper
        - Final version, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 35)
        - Drafts and notes, 1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - United Nations Secretariat [memos and letter of resignation], 1947 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Writings
    - "Postwar American Aid to China", 1947-1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - "Some Effects of the War on Economic Thought in the USA", 1941 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Speeches, notes and drafts, 1940-1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 41)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1837-1981, undated; Series III
  This series consists of family records, memorabilia, and Ray's educational materials, arranged alphabetically by subject. Ray's diaries document his personal life and experiences as a Yale undergraduate. Class folders contain class notes, papers, and related materials. Family papers consist of memorabilia and thorough biographical papers documenting the Ray family history. The papers of Jefferson Franklin Ray, Sr. document his life and work as a Baptist missionary in Japan and elsewhere, and include sermons, autobiographical sketches and many writings.
  - Awards, 1922-1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1924-1976, undated (Box 10, Folder 39855)
  - Education
    - High school essays and report cards, 1922, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - College (Box 11)
      - Awards, 1926-1927 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Classes
        - Astronomy, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
        - Chemistry, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
        - Chinese culture and institutions, 1924-1925, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
        - English, 1924, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
        - Ethics, 1924, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
        - Geology, 1925, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
        - History, Old Testament, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
        - History, renaissance, 1924-1925, undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
        - Latin, 1924, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
        - Philosophy of science and religion, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
        - Philosophy of the state, 1924-1925, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
        - Political science, 1924-1925, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
        - Psychology, 1924, undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
      - Essays, undated (Box 12, Folder 28)
      - "A Fox Story" [fiction by Ray], undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
      - Notes, 1925-1926, undated (Box 12, Folder 30)
      - Poetry, 1923-1926, undated (Box 12, Folder 31)
      - Scholastic record, 1923-1926 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Yearbook, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Family
    - Biographical [information on Pettus and Ray families], 1919-1967, undated (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - Clippings, 1941-1946, undated (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - Higgins, Mary Elisabeth Ray [estate of], 1960-1981, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - Ray, Hermon S. [songs by], 1952-1969 (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - Ray, Jefferson Franklin Sr.
      - Awards, 1922-1953 (Box 13, Folder 38)
      - Estate, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 39)
      - Memorial service, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 40)
      - "Missionary Album" [Foreign Mission Board publication], 1959 (Box 13, Folder 41)
      - Passports and related materials, 1919-1947 (Box 13, Folder 42)
      - Sermons [in Japanese], undated (Box 13, Folder 43)
      - Writings
        - Autobiographical, 1895-1908, undated (Box 13, Folder 44)
        - General, 1893-1929, undated (Box 13, Folder 45)
    - "Tippah County Death Notices," 1837-1936, 1976, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 46)
    - Yearbooks, Judson College and Jackson High School, 1904, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 47-48)
  - Finances, 1939-1940, undated (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - Insurance, 1919-1964 (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - Medical records, 1935-1950 (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - Passports and related materials, 1921-1952, undated (Box 14, Folder 53)
- Photographs, 1879-1961, undated; Series IV
  This series is arranged in three sections: albums, identified images, and unidentified images. "Albums" contains photographs that have been removed from albums created by the Ray family. Though some photographs document missionary activity in Asia, almost all of the photographs from the albums are family snapshots. Identified photographs are arranged by individual and region. Unidentified photographs are arranged by subject. Almost all photographs are black and white, undated, and generally range in size from 2" x 4" to 8" x 10".
  - Albums, 1902-1956, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-8)
  - Identified images
    - Austern, Tommy, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Bache & Company [convention], 1956
      General note
      See also: Oversize, Box 19
    - Family, 1923-1939, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Lend-Lease Administration, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Missionary work [Jefferson Franklin Ray, Sr., Daisy Winston Pettus Ray, et al], undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Pettus, Edmund Winston, undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Pettus, Henry J., undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Ray, Celeste Balfour, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Ray, Daisy Winston Pettus, 1879-1939, undated (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Ray, Emma Pettus, 1922
      See: Oversize, Box 19
    - Ray, Jefferson Franklin, 1923-1939, undated (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Ray, Mary Elisabeth, 1951-1961, undated (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Rodevitch, Maya, 1942, undated (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - China, undated (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - South Asia, Middle East, undated (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified images
    - Children, undated (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Individuals, undated (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Groups, undated (Box 18, Folder 24-26)
    - Asia, undated (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous [positives and negatives], undated (Box 18, Folder 28-29)
- Oversize
  - Images, 1922, 1956, undated (Box 19)